You've talked about how healthcare needs
to be emotionally [music] ready before
it can be technologically ready. What
does that look like at the leadership
[music] level to you?
You want to make sure that everyone you
hire is emotionally intelligent and
ready enough to be in that environment.
[music] You can create a trauma-informed
just culture environment first. You're
now having the psychological [music]
safety that staff are looking for.
That's what staff are looking for when
they come to work every day. At this
point, I was [music] really able to mask
and hide how much all of this secondary
[music] trauma was affecting me by
walking right into the room with a smile
on my face and not letting it affect the
patient. Cuz we were like, "Wow, we have
about 20 years [music] of this, 25 years
of this weighing on us, weighing on our
hearts, weighing on our mind." And this
is the first time we're really realizing
like, oh my god, I just 23 years with
trauma three to four, five times a day
happening. [music]
Susie Branagan has spent her career
helping healthcare organizations rebuild
trust from the inside out, shifting
cultures from blame to learning, from
burnout to belonging. A trauma-informed
nurse executive and AI ethics advocate,
she's helped leaders reimagine what
readiness really means in the digital
age. Not just new systems, but new kinds
of empathy. Susie, welcome to the sign
room and thank you for taking the time
to be here with me today.
Well, thank you for having me and thank
you for such a wonderful introduction.
Well, it's a pleasure to have you. I've
been looking forward to this because
we've had some really great
conversations and we're talking about
readiness and there's a lot of
conversations happening around how are
we going to be able to trust AI and all
of that, but I think we've gotten a
little bit too too much ahead of
ourselves and we really haven't
addressed some of the really basic
things and it's really the human
readiness gap I think that you've you've
mentioned to me before.
So, you've talked about how healthcare
needs to be emotionally ready before it
can be technologically ready. What does
that look like at the leadership level
to you?
Sure. You know,
basically over the last I don't know 20
something years, especially as of late
after co, you know, staff are growing um
less and less trust trustful of their
leadership, right? Um you know, they're
always promised these revolutionary
solutions um such as even new EHR
systems, right? So, oh, we're going to
give you this new EHR. It's going to be
wonderful. We're going to go from MedTek
to epic. Well, guess what? Like you need
to have a team that is emotionally ready
and feels safe on their unit first
before you introduce these new things
because you may think they're great for
the staff as a leader or you know senior
leader but until you're actually working
on the unit using the system and having
a healthy atmosphere around that you're
not going to be successful. So, I know
from personal experience, even something
as simple as going from MedTek to Epic,
when we did that on one of my units,
thankfully I had a pretty healthy staff
that felt pretty trustworthy of me,
that, you know, took years of management
skills and building trust and all that
and using just culture, which I know
we're going to talk about, but they
still were skeptical like, you know, I
don't really like many tech. It feels
like the Oregon Trail. It's it's just
green and white. I don't, you know,
nothing's colorful. It's hard to read.
there's no ability to uh you know it's
it's not up in with the times right but
then here comes Epic and the way it's
rolled out is very important anything
that's rolled out is super important you
know before you do that you have to make
sure that
everybody's ready first you're asking
their opinion on what they think may go
wrong what what do they think are going
to be the biggest challenges and then
try to conquer those things before you
implement don't just come on to a unit
one day with all the epic gurus and say,
"Today we're moving over to Epic. Okay,
get your wows out and here it is. It's
beautiful, isn't it? It's so colorful,
right?" But Epic can be very hard to
navigate. Um, I remember the experience
of some staff like some were super
computer savvy and learn quickly and
others were not computer savvy and had
relied on like simple notes before and
this was too much for them. So at the
end of the day, I'll always come back to
the fact that if you don't have a
healthy, trustworthy staff first, you
can't really implement really anything.
We just we've been through so much moral
injury over the last decade,
right?
You know, it's understandable that staff
are like, you know, I don't really want
to do something new right now. I'm fine
with what I'm doing. I mean, we're
underst staffed to begin with. Let me
just let me just run my day, right?
Yes. But if it's done the right way and
other things are implemented first, you
know, we can be successful, you know,
when people feel unsafe, it's like an
actual fact that the frontal cortex like
completely goes offline, like you're
completely just not there. And to
implement all this stuff and have that,
you know, feeling in the background for
every staff member, you know, 100 staff
people, that's going to be hard to
conquer. So, yeah, you have to have that
trust back. Now I I remember going
through an implementation myself a
number of years ago and yeah there's a
lot of moving parts and I think the
hardest hardest thing was just as you
said is overcoming some of the the
obstacles that are really related to
that the trust factor and for people to
be comfortable there all all you
mentioned the the different skills skill
levels I mean these are all things that
were really challenging to navigate but
real things I mean I felt terrible some
of my staff that had used Meditech their
entire their career,
right?
You know, when moving to Epic, they
crumbled. You know, it went from having
no overtime, not really, you know,
having the normal stresses of working in
a healthcare environment, but like I'm
telling like two to three hours of
overtime every day to get their work
done on the computer because they just
didn't understand despite the training
classes and the online classes and the
people that walk around with the cookies
and pizza and help you at the computer
for a few minutes. like that that wasn't
enough. If they don't have the computer
skill background or just their whole
career has been using one system, you
just you have to have other things in
place to support. So, it does take a
leader that walks the unit constantly
during implementations. Like you live
and breathe there all three shifts.
Yeah. And I you've touched on something
that I think is really important too
when you're talking about the trust
issue. There's been an erosion of it for
probably more than more than a decade,
possibly two. I I had a conversation
recently with a gentleman named Larry
[ __ ] He's a he's a clinical
psychologist. Some of the the stats that
he shared with me were staggering, but
it it reinforces what intuitively I
think we know. Really basic things like
do you trust the government? You know,
20 years ago, probably eight out of 10
people would have said yes,
right? trusting law enforcement, clergy,
your physician, your co-workers, the
CEO.
Yep.
Across the board, those numbers have
dropped like a rock. We're talking
absolutely like a rock
in the 20s in most every one of those
categories. So the culture has to be
something that gets addressed in the
process of this too because it's a
really really big shift that we're
asking people to go along with us. And
if they don't trust guidance that we're
giving them and how useful it is, they
don't feel psychologically safe, who's
going to raise their hand to point out
something that actually could be
automated because they're not going to
trust you're going to let them have keep
their job.
I mean these are
Yeah. And I think the big difference too
with like an epic and then like AI,
right? So when we implemented epic back
probably 10 whatever years ago probably
less that seemed intense to everyone
right yes now you have AI coming which
also seems extremely intense but also
as someone as a that has used AI on on
my child psychiatry unit you know a
challenge that the staff have is like
meeting halfway right so the AI is only
there to help you with certain steps and
to make your job easier that's what it
should be doing not harder Yes,
but you as a human being always have to
check the work, right? You don't you
cannot just rely on AI. So AI is there
to help you and it can be extremely
helpful. It helped prevent so many
falls, elopments, suicide attempts, self
harm, you know, episodes. But at the end
of the day, you know, in numbers, you
know, looking at the numbers and you can
get reports and stuff on on your AI
system that we used, you know, each
co-worker was different in how they
utilized it. Some relied on it
completely and then others were like,
"Okay, I trust that it's working, but
I'm going to go check the patient
anyways because something seems off, you
So with AI, we have to make sure that
staff
not only are ready for it and feel
supported, but also don't use it as like
a crutch and use it as, you know, a care
replacement basically.
You've used the term just culture. Um,
I'd love for you to kind of unrack that
a little bit for me. How can
organizations use just culture
principles to bridge the readiness gap
that we've been talking about?
Sure. So just culture is like my
favorite thing in the world, as you
know. Oh, I talk about it. Uh, nauseium
because I feel like you cannot have
success on in any any organization like
not even just healthcare. I'm currently
working with a steel industry uh
organization with just culture. I mean,
everyone that has an employee or two
should start the basis of their unit
with this with this. So, in a perfect
world, if you were to open a brand new
unit and hire from scratch and have, you
know, 75 new employees, the first thing
that I would do is train all the staff
in Just Culture what it is and make sure
that the manager that's running that
unit runs a Just Culture environment.
Um, so, you know, for those that don't
know, I mean, I think at this point in
healthcare, a lot of people have either
heard of it or are definitely using it.
some of the presentations that I've done
at schools for nurse leaders, it was
about a 70% had heard about it and about
55 to 60% were actually utilizing it.
And we need to bring that number up
because stats don't lie. Turnover rates
decrease. Staff are just way happier
coming to work when you have an
environment where you know you can speak
up about concerns. You know that you can
go tell your boss that you made a
mistake. you know that everyone is, you
know, in a healthy environment that
toxicity is not tolerated from
everything from being late to work to
making a MET error if you can get just
culture down pat on your unit first. Um,
also making sure that depending on the
unit you're on, but it really doesn't
matter because any unit can experience
trauma, but as an extreme example, you
know, if you're running a child
psychiatry unit or a children's ICU, a
highly acute ICU, that's going to
involve a lot of secondary trauma for
the staff, right? They're going to be
seeing a lot of sad, sad stuff. You want
to make sure that everyone you hire is
emotionally intelligent and ready enough
to be in that environment, you know, and
that they're trained in traumainformed
culture and how to treat the patient
that's going through trauma, but also
the manager needs to be traumainformed
to make sure that they they can support
staff that go through that stuff. So, if
you can create a trauma-informed, just
culture environment first, you're now
having the psychological safety that
staff are looking for. That's what staff
are looking for when they come to work
every day at this point. You know, I
unfortunately along with a lot of people
my age in nursing didn't really feel
like we had that support. And it wasn't
anyone's fault necessarily. It was more
the education around it. just just
culture and trauma-informed care was not
spoken about at all. Like when I worked
at Children's Hospital when I was, you
know, younger, starting out my career,
wonderful, wonderful experience, great
staff, great manager, everything. But it
just wasn't a thing that we talked about
yet. It wasn't a thing that anyone
trained in. You know, if you don't have
those two things first and then you're
trying to implement something new,
you're not going to be successful. Any
new implementation, if they feel like
they can come to you and be like, I get
that you wanted to do this. I get that
this system is what we're going to go
with. You know, senior leadership hates
the word pilot. They don't ever want us
to say pilot on a unit because it's
definitely not a pilot,
right?
From my experience, nothing's been a
pilot and it's always going to be
permanent no matter what. And that's
always been kind of a problem, right? As
a manager, you're like the hamburger in
between the two buns, right? And you
have to tell staff,
right? you know, okay, this new AI
system's coming to us, and you can't say
the word pilot, but you do want to kind
of tell them like this is not going
away. So, you feel like you're lying to
the staff almost. You're like, oh, we're
going to try this, but at the end of the
day, it's it's it's there forever. So,
yeah, that can be definitely hard hard
conversations to have. No, you're
talking about some things that are
incredibly important. And I don't know
that people really think
think about the the the impact and the
emotional toll that working in that kind
of an environment would be like for a
nurse. I think most of us have met
nurses that are absolutely wonderful and
they're they're always on top of things.
They're they I've always got a smile,
but you know, I don't know that I really
realized until having conversations with
you, you know, what what that looks like
for them on a day-to-day basis because
they are seeks and some things that are
really difficult.
Yeah. So, I can say that I was um and
I'm not tooting my own horn. I just know
this because I can't think of a day that
I ever snapped on a patient really. And
I'm proud of that. Did I get frustrated
over things? Yeah. But like I was good
about even going into the bathroom of
that room and taking a breath and
whatever, but I was really able to mask
and hide how much all of this secondary
trauma was affecting me by walking right
into the room with a smile on my face
and not letting it affect the patient.
That's really hard to do. And I think
that's why healthcare workers,
especially in my generation, are really
seeking a lot of like therapy and all
that because we're like, wow, we have
about 20 years of this, 25 years of this
weighing on us, weighing on our hearts,
weighing on our mind. And this is the
first time we're really realizing like,
oh my god, I just 23 years with trauma
three to four, five times a day
happening. And that can be, like I said,
that can be any unit. I mean, emergency
rooms, I mean, think about what they see
every day. Oncology units, think about
what they see, you know, and you could
say, oh, you know, what about posttop?
People are just getting their knee
replacement or they're, you know,
whatever. Well, you know, maybe they
hurt their knee permanently and they
were a star athlete and, you know, now
they're never going to play again.
That's traumatic for them.
And how are you supporting them in that?
So it is a it was an unguided 20some
years of how to manage patients um you
know and and people if you're going to
become a manager that are themselves
going through some PTSD of what they've
seen.
So yeah, you'll see people that cannot
hold it in at the bedside and they kind
of show their frustration and that's why
just culture is important in that aspect
because I would have some staff
sometimes that would show their
frustration to the patient. But with
just culture, you want to make sure
you're bringing that person in with no
judgment in first and saying, you know,
what happened today in room 10, not I
heard that you yelled at patient so and
so. What you know what's wrong with you
type of thing. And I know that sounds
harsh, but like people talk like that,
unfortunately.
So, you know, my approach would have
been, you know, Sally, you know, tell me
what happened on the night shift last
night. Did you have an okay shift? And
that usually brings up, oh, you heard
about what happened. Okay. And I'm like,
well, you know, let me hear your side,
though. And you use the gentle,
non-judgmental. And you'll get um you'll
get a lot more out of someone because
they know you're not there to just im
immediately. It's called like the
whack-a-ole syndrome. you're not there
to just be like, well, you're written up
because you yelled at patient ABC,
right? So, yeah, it's just it takes a
lot of work, a lot of support. And
that's why with AI coming, you know, we
have to remember that at the end of the
day, most staff that are coming to work
are mentally exhausted, but they love
what they do. And if you're going to
introduce something new, you want to
make them feel empowered, and you want
them to feel like they have a choice,
per se. I know, like I said, most of
these systems come and they're going to
stay, but like take feedback, do
surveys, right? I used to send out
little Google surveys to my staff
anonymous, you know, so they didn't have
to feel like they had their name on it
about, you know, the epic roll out or
when we did hourly rounding rollouts,
leader rounding rollouts, all that
stuff. You got to have a shared
governance.
This is this is really important stuff.
I I I can't I can't even overstate this.
There's just no way. I think that, you
know, I think it's really interesting
that you're you're doing something even
in the steel industry kind of goes to
the heart of what we're what we're just
talking about in terms of that the trust
erosion. Doesn't matter what industry
we're talking about.
These these things really need to be
addressed across the board and for
leaders to hear this from you I think is
a really really important and valuable.
Yeah. I mean, it's really a foolproof
system if you utilize a just culture
environment and trauma-informed care
environment because, you know, like I I
think we've discussed before, I've had
staff that, you know, we've coached and
coached and worked through the just
culture algorithm and, you know, they've
they still couldn't really get it right
and whether it was behavioral or
practice. And at the end of the day, if
unfortunately, you know, their mistakes
were just repetitive and it was causing
a lot of harm or it just was, you know,
they weren't learning from it or they
couldn't change, you know, I have staff
that still talk to me this day that are
like, you know, if you never let me go,
I would never have like learned that
what I was doing was like really wrong.
And, you know, now I'm in therapy or now
I, you know, only work in hospice
because I found that I like to work
independently and not in a team. And
that's okay, too, right? So some people
are great on a team, some people want to
work independently and there's a place
for everybody in healthcare really. So
we you've said you said that emotional
intelligence should sit alongside data
literacy in the conversations we've had
before. It's a core competency that you
know you believe that leaders need to
have.
Yeah,
I agree with you by the way. How do you
teach that as a leader in a techdriven
environment?
Okay, so it's really hard to teach
emotional intelligence, right? It it's
kind of, you know, you can't really
teach someone to be empathetic or, you
know, if someone is a genuinely, you
know, I had a nurse once tell me when I
worked in the ICU with children, she
used to say like, Susie, you have a
heart of gold. She's like, I am cold as
ice. And I was like, what? And she's
like, well, I just don't I do this work
because I can like I can handle and I
don't take it home with me. And I and
I'm like, are you saying I do? And she's
like, "No, I can just tell you really
are like beyond passionate about that."
I said, "Well, there's positives and
negatives to that, too." You know, you
can be overly emotional and it can
affect your personal life, right? Like I
had to sometimes take a step back and
think like after my shift riding the
train home like, "Wow, I spent way too
much time in that room today." And you
know I I I neglect not neglected but
like I spent you know an hour in this
room and only 20 minutes in this room
and there's a lot of guilt that comes up
in nursing of like did I spend enough
time with everybody. emotional
intelligence has so many it's like a
spectrum, right? You can have zero
emotional intelligence and that's going
to be pretty bad, right? But you can
have like a little bit and you have and
you work on certain things and you have
skills in other ways and as long as
you're open to learning about what
you're kind of what's rubbing people the
wrong way, rubbing patients the wrong
way, then you know there's there's a
positive outlook for you. But yeah,
emotional intelligence itself is hard to
teach, but traumainformed
like language and therapeutic talk is
something that can be taught. And it's
really about the individual being
willing to learn. So, you know, if you
have no emotional intelligence and you
won't sit down with me in my office and
talk about it, I I I can't help you. The
key to people being able to be at their
best at work is being open to feedback,
right? So,
does that answer your question?
It did. It kind of go a little bit
deeper on the the the topic of of
empathy. Um, and this is a strange area
for me because I'm feeling like there
should be some guard rails that we put
in place so that we don't even try to
make AI seem so human that people get
comfortable right away and trust it.
Yeah.
Because I think we already have a
problem in that in that area.
Mhm. with the way people are being able
to engage directly so easily with people
across the planet. Social media has so
many hooks into it that people are
really easily trusting things that they
just shouldn't.
Absolutely.
So from a nursing perspective, what do
you think we need to know to really
design AI solutions with regard to
presence, empathy, and situational
awareness? Because these are to me just
they're inherently human. I don't know.
that we really want to mess with that
AI, but someone's going to for sure.
Right. Right. So, I think um there's a
happy medium with AI when it comes to
caring for the patient and and being
gentle with the staff and how much
dedication they have to their own trade,
right? They come into work, they have
their their um their routine and they
have their way that they do things. And
now here this is this new product we're
using, whatever. We have to make sure
when designing these products that there
is empathy involved but not so much
empathy that the computer or the the
robot is taking over the human factor.
That is the next step. Right? So a good
example of that is, you know, people
that have been using just simple chap
GPT or claude to almost like a as a
therapist or like to vent about really
serious mental, emotional health issues,
AI can take it a step too far where it
should have these things in place where
it says, you know what, Jay, you know,
it's been wonderful talking with you. I
can see that you're really struggling.
here are some crisis hotlines that I'd
like you to, you know, check in with
because I I have to stop here. I'm not a
health care professional,
right?
And, you know, these these these apps
do, you know, give you crisis hotlines
and all that, too, but they do that like
way far in. We we've even had I'm not
sure I think everyone's heard of the
family that is suing a certain company
for the fact that their son was almost
encouraged to to end his life through AI
because
right
AI probably thought it was being
supportive but it was actually like
supporting the child's urge to do it and
we need to make sure that doesn't
happen. It's important that when
engaging with AI that you feel
supported, you feel empowered, but you
don't feel like it's completely making
all the decisions for both you as the
patient and this caregiver. Cuz I'm sure
somewhere down the road, and I think
it's probably already out there.
Patients are going to be interfacing
with an AI something at the bedside.
It's I I guarantee it's going to be
around discharge teaching. Someone's
going to wheel in a computer and say,
you know, you're going to be discharged
at 4 p.m. today. Um, you're going to sit
here for a few minutes if you don't
mind, and I'm going to have our friend,
whatever the product's going to be, you
know, go over your discharge paperwork,
right? But then what happens when
there's questions, right?
The that robot may not be ready to
answer those questions. And a lot of
those questions may be very like
emotionally driven,
right? So we just have to have a happy
medium. Um I have some really awesome I
call them friends and colleagues per se
because we are great friends through
LinkedIn this year both entrepreneurs.
They they are his name is Timmy and
Courtney um and they are creating uh
what's called Compathia and they are
specifically looking to create a product
where nursing students that are working
in like sim labs and training during
like college and even like for a new job
as a new nurse to have the robot help
support them in how to deal with like
crisis mental health situations which is
phenomenal because when I was a student
nurse and became became a new nurse. I
didn't really have any preparation for
what I was going to see. I'm actually
writing a book right now on all of, you
know, my my entire career and what I
kind of went through blindly at first
because colleges back then really
focused on anatomy, physiology. Uh, you
know, I I even took a bunch of theology
classes during my nurse, you know what I
mean? Like they nobody ever talked about
actual mental health as much as they
should have. But I think that the crisis
has, you know, risen over the years for
sure. But thankfully now we have people
like Timmy and Courtney who are really
trying to create that, you know, hard
stop right out of college or during
school of like, I get that you're going
to walk into a room and have a patient
that, you know, attempted suicide. Let's
talk about what that may look like. And
then they may have that mannequin talk
to them, you know, and and say like, you
know, I'm really thinking about ending
my life. And then the student has
interaction with that without having to
do it in person with a real patient
first. Right? Imagine walking into your
first assignment on a unit as a new
nurse and having the assignment be, oh,
you're going to go in and today you have
two patients and one was involved in a
car bombing in Iraq and he has headto
toe gauze. um and wounds and is not able
to eat or drink, whatever. And then in
this room, you're going to have a girl
who um you know, managed to uh sneak
past her dad after school and hang
herself. You could have those two kids
at once,
right?
And not know how to handle that at all
because you didn't get the training or
the in, you know, teaching around that.
utilizing these um these mannequins to
pre, you know, to to proactively
support you and how you would handle
that situation when you walk into it.
Cuz I know I personally walked into
those situations blindly and I gave that
example as real examples. So I did have
two patients at the same time with that
those type of um you know situations and
I got through it. I feel like I did a
great job. I'm proud of myself, but man,
do I wish that I had had more education
and just preparation and practice around
around these situations.
When I think back to, you know, nursing
school and clinicals, I don't remember a
single clinical where my instructor
really was like grabbing me in the
hallway after a difficult patient
interaction or anything. It was always
around like met administration, making
sure there were no air bubbles in the
tubing, you know, did you put the Foley
correctly at the bedside and all that
stuff is extremely important, but there
was a lot of focus on the physiological
stuff and the equipment, right, than
there was on the actual human
interaction and what to expect in
certain situations. Um,
you know, just I just think back and I'm
like, wow, some of the stuff I got
through with zero preparation [laughter]
was insane. It's really crazy. Crazy.
I think that's what makes your voice so
important at this point in time for
because of where we are. This is the
biggest transformation that I think any
of us have ever seen in our lifetimes.
There's no question about that.
That's awesome. Yeah, I'm an, you know,
I'm an open book about my journey and my
trauma and PTSD. I wouldn't change a
thing in the world. I wouldn't go back
and not work anywhere I worked. Thing I
landed everywhere I did for a reason.
But what I do plan on doing for the rest
of my career is making sure that as many
nurses and techs and any healthcare
worker that I come across feels the
support and safety that I didn't really
get because it can make or break your
life sometimes too, right? Like I've
managed to lead a very productive, happy
life with marriage, children, all that
and I'm happy. that there are people
that the trauma is so bad in healthcare
that they don't they can't maintain
relationships or substance abuse happens
and even suicide the suicide rates and
self harm rates for healthcare workers
are skyrocketing like they're the number
is is terrible and we need to really
hone in on that
right
you know
so as we're kind of wrapping things up
first of all this has been amazing for
me I I think we could talk for hours
always we have,
right? But if you could give a a piece
of advice to leaders around emotional
readiness and how to manage and lead
with this AI transformation, what would
you talk to them about?
I would I would definitely start with
getting out onto your unit or your
whatever type of floor that you're
managing. Um, and and don't just round
and ask how people's day is. And you
know, you know, you'll see a lot of
rounding, but the rounding can be very
obvious that it's actually checking if
people are like doing their work and
things like that. You want to make sure
when you're rounding that it's genuine
and that you're asking people like, "Do
you need boots on the ground help?"
Like, I used to wear a suit, but I wore
a cheap suit because I was a leader, but
then I also wanted to get my hands dirty
if staff needed help and then I knew
that suit could get washed or thrown
out, whatever. So, you always want to be
ready and willing to go into a room and
help a staff member. To my own
detriment, sometimes I would go into
rooms of patients that had been, you
know, historically very difficult and
staff needed a break. And I would say,
"Don't worry, I got it. I'm I'm going to
go in there and I'll spend some time
with her." And I felt like I did a good
job. It was my jam. I I loved going in
and talking to people that needed help
mentally, but it does take a toll on
you. So I would say to the leader like
helping out and supporting but not also
taking on a ton of the burden. You have
to like equal out the load basically,
right?
And just really, you know, really asking
people genuinely, how can I help you?
Spreading the work out, making sure
everything's fair, making sure your team
leaders are are solid and not just
because they're looking to make an extra
couple of dollars an hour. And because
I've had people that are like, "Oh, I
can I want to be charge nurse." And I'm
like, "Uh,
are you doing it for the money or
because because there's a you can tell a
difference between yeah,
a charge nurse that's in it to help her
team or his team
or for extra money." So really choosing
your sub leaders wisely is very
important. And that will help as well
during implementation of new products or
new applications because if you have
charge nurses and team leaders that also
believe in it, you know, it's you're
going to go farther. But just be kind.
Um have a genuine positive attitude
despite if stuff's hitting the ceiling,
you need to maintain your emotions. So I
consider myself a pretty emotional
person in certain aspects, but when it
comes to chaos and crisis that like
shuts off and I become like a machine of
like how can I help you? What do you
need? Blah blah blah. You need to be
ready for anything as a leader and not
have like a flight or fight orflight
mode look on your face because if you
look scared, the staff are going to be
like, "Oh my god, well Susie's scared.
What's really happening here?"
you kind of have to put on a a brave
face. Um, and just
right,
you know, be in it for the right reason.
Make sure that you're in management for
the right reason. Um, because people
will see that, right,
if it's not the right reason.
That's a really important thing to to be
pointing out and people need to not lose
sight of that.
Yeah. Susie, as as people have have been
listening to to you this morning, they
they may have some thoughts and ideas of
perhaps how you might be able to help
them.
Yeah.
How can people get in touch with you?
Where can they learn about what you're
what you're doing and how it can apply
to whatever industry even as I as I've
just learned, not just a healthcare
crisis we're dealing with?
Yes, it's a people crisis. It's a the
world is filled with people in every
industry that are just overloaded with
everything. Like technology can be
amazing, but it also can take over our
lives too. You know, doom scrolling, all
of that can lead to depression and all
of that. So, really, so yeah, you can
reach me on I I have my regular page
that I've always had for a while. Um,
just Susie Branagan on LinkedIn. And
then I do have my new business page,
Susie Branagan Consulting, that
you I encourage you to follow. Both
pages I kind of post the similar stuff
because I have followers on both and you
know it's important to get out to every
industry what I'm doing and trying to
achieve. But then on my consulting kind
of page, I put in examples of um you
know assessments that I do. Some of the
things that I do is, you know, if your
organization is not sure what's going on
on your unit, whether it's uh behavioral
issues, just general practice issues, I
do these assessments tailored to your
type of unit. So, if it's oncology, it's
tailored to that. If it's emergency
room, it's tailored to that. If it's the
steel industry, it's tailored to that.
So we would do a full assessment on you
know anonymous either the leaders can
take it for you know taking kind of a
pulse on what the current atmosphere is
like the culture and then it's also for
the staff hand out 100 assessments to
your staff and have them hand them in
anonymous anonymously if you are open to
change and willingness you should be
ready to hear whatever right you should
be ready to hear that people aren't
happy about their lunch breaks or people
aren't happy about whatever
right
and So, I've had some success really
being able to chime in and hone in on
themes and and repetitive, you know,
answers and then work with the leader.
We were talking about quality to create
how we're going to implement um the
culture of an organization.
I also do culture training, the trauma
informed training it is when you're
building AI continuing education. I love
doing that with
kind of in the process after New
Hampshire at St. think about
operationalizing that what do leaders
really need on that they're approaching
properly and it's getting
I know I'm getting a lot into the DNA of
the company I can kind of cover
leadership in any realm. So if you're
looking to hire with heart and not just
look at a resume and say oh they have a
4.0 you know, they look great. Like, I'm
your girl to talk to about cuz I was
able to manage units with people that
never even had a college degree and they
were the best caregivers that I've ever
ex, you know, had the pleasure of
managing.
So, stuff like that. And, you know, I do
one-on-one counseling. I'm not a
counselor, but one-on-one support to
anybody that's going through trauma or
PTSD in the workforce, maybe even left
their job and don't even know where to
go next. I am doing that type of support
as well. So, it's kind of a gambit of
things, but basically, I just want to
help healthcare staff in any way I can.
Really?
No, that's amazing, Susie. It's it's
been fun to to have a conversation with
you. We we always enjoy exploring these
same
really interesting topics. So, thanks
again for taking the time to chat with
me this morning and can't wait to have
you back. I and also I can't wait to
hear what what you're doing next because
it just seems like things are going all
over the place where you're getting they
are
when it rains it pours in a good way.
Yeah. Right. It's a great Sometimes
there's a lull of stuff and you're like,
"Oh, am I doing things right?" And then
you're like, "Okay, I can't even keep up
with all these requests." So, it's nice,
you know, because I'm doing truly what I
was put on earth to do. Like, I couldn't
be at the bedside anymore. I felt like I
put my time in and I needed to be at
home and I'm just loving it because I'm
able to manage myself and and, you know,
really help people all day long. So,
it's it's amazing.
That is very awesome. Appreciate that.
That's it for this episode of the Signal
Room. If today's conversation sparked
something in you, an idea, a challenge,
or a perspective worth amplifying, I'd
love to hear from you. Message me on
LinkedIn or visit cigarroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming
episode. Until next time, stay tuned,
stay curious, and stay human.